<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-04T20:16:49-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Neatline</title><subtitle>Neatline allows scholars, students, and curators to tell stories with maps and timelines.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A (Digital) Declaration of Independence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/07/02/a-digital-declaration-of-independence-with-text-painting-and-map/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A (Digital) Declaration of Independence" /><published>2014-07-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-07-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2014/07/02/a-digital-declaration-of-independence-with-text-painting-and-map</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2014/07/02/a-digital-declaration-of-independence-with-text-painting-and-map/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Z3988&quot; title=&quot;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Focoins.info%3Agenerator&amp;amp;rft.type=&amp;amp;rft.format=text&amp;amp;rft.title=A+%28Digital%29+Declaration+of+Independence&amp;amp;rft.source=Scholars%26%23039%3B+Lab&amp;amp;rft.date=2014-07-02&amp;amp;rft.identifier=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.scholarslab.org%2Fgeospatial-and-temporal%2Fa-digital-declaration-of-independence-with-text-painting-and-map%2F&amp;amp;rft.language=English&amp;amp;rft.subject=Geospatial+and+Temporal&amp;amp;rft.aulast=McClure&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=David&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/essays/a-digital-declaration-of-independence-with-text-painting-and-map/&quot;&gt;dclure.org&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;launch-the-exhibit&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/declaration-of-independence&quot;&gt;Launch the Exhibit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/declaration-of-independence&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/declaration-of-independence-1024x610.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;declaration-of-independence&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;381&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3927&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Way back in the spring of 2012, a couple months before we released the first version of Neatline, I drove up to Washington to give a little demo of the project to the folks at the Library of Congress. I had put together a couple of example exhibits for the presentation, but, the night before, I was bored and found myself brainstorming about Washington-themed projects. On a lark, I downloaded a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/declaration_transcript.html&quot;&gt;scan of the 1823 facsimile of the Declaration of Independence&lt;/a&gt; from the National Archives website, and spent a couple hours tracing polygons around each one of the signatures at the bottom of the document. I showed the exhibit the next day, and had big plans to flesh it out and turn it into a real, showable project. But then I got swept up in the race to get the first release of Neatline out the door before DH2012 in Hamburg, and then sucked into the craziness of the summer conference season, and the project slipped down into the towering stack of things that I could never quite find time to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, though, the idea popped back into my head a couple months ago – maybe because Menlo Park is submerged in a kind of permanent summer, and it pretty much always feels like a good time to eat ice cream and shoot off fireworks. After mulling it over for a couple weeks, I decided to resurrect it from the dead, spruce it up, and post it in time for the 4th of July. So, with two days to spare, here we go – an interactive edition of the Declaration of Independence, tightly coupled with three other “views” in an effort to add dimension to the original document:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A full-text, two-way-linked transcription of the manuscript and the signatures at the bottom. Click on sentences in the transcription to focus on the corresponding region of the scanned image, or click on annotated blocks on the image to scroll the text. 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/transcript.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/transcript-1024x620.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;transcript&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;387&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3931&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;An interactive edition of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trumbull%27s_Declaration_of_Independence&quot;&gt;Trumbull’s “Declaration of Independence” painting&lt;/a&gt;, with each of the faces outlined and interactively linked with the corresponding signature on the document. 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/painting1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/painting1-1024x616.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;painting&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;385&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3940&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;All of which is plastered on top of a map that plots out each of the signers’ hometowns on a custom &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/&quot;&gt;Mapbox&lt;/a&gt; layer, which makes it easy to see how the layout of the signatures maps on to the geographic layout of the colonies. Which, by extension, tracks the future division between Union and Confederate states in the Civil War – Georgia and the Carolinas look awful lonely over on the far left side of the document. 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/map1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/map1-1024x615.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;map&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;384&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3939&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/ol&amp;gt; 
Once I positioned the layers, annotated the signatures and faces, and plotted out the hometowns, I realized that I had painted myself into an interesting little corner from an information design standpoint – it was difficult to quickly move back and forth between the three main sections of the exhibit. In a sense, this is an inherent characteristic of deeply-zoomed interfaces. The ability to focus really closely on any one of the three visual grids – which is what makes it possible to mix them all together into a single environment – has the side effect of making the other two increasingly distant and inaccessible, more and more so the further down you go. For example, once you’ve focused in on Thomas Jefferson’s face in the Trumbull painting, it’s quite a chore to manually navigate to the corresponding signature on the document – you have to zoom back, pan the map up towards the scanned image, find the signature (often no easy task), and then zoom back down.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;This is especially annoying in this case, since this potential for &lt;em&gt;comparison&lt;/em&gt; is a big part of what’s interesting about the content. What I really wanted, I realized, was to be able to switch back and forth in a really simple, fluid way among the different instantiations of any individual person on the document, painting, and map – I wanted to be able to flip through them like a slideshow, to round up all the little partial representations of the person and hold them side-by-side in my head. So, as an experiment, I whipped up a little batch of custom UI components (built with the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://facebook.github.io/react/&quot;&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; library, which fits in like a dream with Neatline’s Javascript API) that provide a “toggling” interface for each individual signer, and the exhibit as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;By default, when you hit the page, three top-level buttons in the right corner of the window link to the the three main sections of the exhibit – the hometowns plotted along the eastern seaboard, the declaration over the midwest, and the painting over the southeast. In addition to the three individual buttons, there’s also a little “rotate” button that automatically cycles through the three regions, which makes it easy to toggle around without looking away from the map to move the cursor:&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/exhibit-buttons.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/exhibit-buttons.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;exhibit-buttons&quot; width=&quot;603&quot; height=&quot;138&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3937&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;More useful, though, it’s possible to bind any of the individual signers to the widget by clicking on the annotations. For example, if I click on Thomas Jefferson’s face in the painting, the name locks into place next to the buttons, which now point to the representations of that specific person in the exhibit – “Text” links to Jefferson’s signature, “Painting” to his face, and “Map” to Monticello:&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/signer-toggle.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/signer-toggle-1024x840.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;signer-toggle&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;525&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3942&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;Once you’ve activated one of the signers, click on the name to show an overlay with a picture and biography, pulled from a public domain book published by the National Park Service called Signers of the Declaration:&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bio-overlay.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/bio-overlay-1024x624.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bio-overlay&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;390&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3943&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;This is pretty straightforward on the map and document, where there’s always a one-to-one correspondence between an annotation and one of the signers. Things get more complicated on the map, though, where it’s possible for a single location to be associted with more than one signer. Philadelphia, for example, was home to Robert Morris, Benjamin Rush, Benjamin Franklin, John Morton, and George Clymer, so I had to write a little widget to make it possible to hone in on just one of the five after clicking the dot:&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/philadelphia.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/philadelphia-1024x377.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;philadelphia&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;235&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3945&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;Last but not least, each sentence in the document itself is annotated and wired up with the corresponding text transcription on the left – click on the image to scroll the text, or click on the text to focus the image:&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/text.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/text-1024x617.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;text&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;385&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3947&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

            &lt;p&gt;Happy fourth!&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>dm4fn</name></author><summary type="html">[Cross-posted from dclure.org] Launch the Exhibit Way back in the spring of 2012, a couple months before we released the first version of Neatline, I drove up to Washington to give a little demo of the project to the folks at the Library of Congress. I had put together a couple of example exhibits for&amp;hellip;. More.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creating themes for individual Neatline exhibits</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/04/01/creating-themes-for-individual-neatline-exhibits/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creating themes for individual Neatline exhibits" /><published>2014-04-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-04-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2014/04/01/creating-themes-for-individual-neatline-exhibits</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2014/04/01/creating-themes-for-individual-neatline-exhibits/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Z3988&quot; title=&quot;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Focoins.info%3Agenerator&amp;amp;rft.type=&amp;amp;rft.format=text&amp;amp;rft.title=Creating+themes+for+individual+Neatline+exhibits&amp;amp;rft.source=Scholars%26%23039%3B+Lab&amp;amp;rft.date=2014-04-01&amp;amp;rft.identifier=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.scholarslab.org%2Fgeospatial-and-temporal%2Ftheming-neatline-exhibits%2F&amp;amp;rft.language=English&amp;amp;rft.subject=Geospatial+and+Temporal&amp;amp;rft.aulast=McClure&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=David&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
Neatline makes it possible to create separate themes for individual exhibits, which is useful if you want to host a collection of self-contained Neatline projects on a single site. To get started, fork the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/neatline-theme-template&quot;&gt;exhibit starter theme&lt;/a&gt;, which abstracts out the style, layout, and UX of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/logs/project-gemini-over-baja-california/&quot;&gt;Project Gemini over Baja California&lt;/a&gt; exhibit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the coolest but most under-documented features in Neatline is the ability to create separate themes for each individual exhibit. Since Neatline exhibits are just one particular type of “view” inside of Omeka, it’s always been possible to customize the styling and layout at the level of the Omeka theme. Changes the the Omeka theme, though, propagate to all the exhibits on the site. In many cases, this is ideal – if you have a collection of closely-related Neatline projects, all part of the same thematic umbrella, it makes sense that they should all look more or less the same. For examples of this, check out Jeremy’s beautiful &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/astrolabe&quot;&gt;Astrolabe&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/neatscape&quot;&gt;Neatscape&lt;/a&gt; themes for Omeka, which were designed with Neatline projects in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other cases, though, this can be a real hindrance. Sometimes it can make sense to host a number of self-contained Neatline exhibits in the same installation of Omeka. For example, imagine you’re using Neatline in a big lecture course, and you split the class up into 10-15 groups of students, all working on separate exhibits. As the semester draws to an end, some of the groups want to use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/announcements/neatline-text/&quot;&gt;NeatlineText&lt;/a&gt; plugin, and need a layout that positions the exhibit narrative on the side of the screen, flush with the edge of the window. But other groups are just threading the text content into the record bodies, and don’t want a big, empty container element taking up space on the screen. How to handle both at once? Or, for a concrete example, take a look at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/&quot;&gt;Neatline Labs&lt;/a&gt; site, which I use a sandbox for little Neatline-powered experiments and feature demos. By design, these projects are all totally different – different content, different layouts, different Javascript interactions, etc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/panorama.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/panorama-1024x88.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;panorama&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;88&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-10046&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be annoying to have to spin up a completely new instance of Omeka for each of these projects. To get around this, Neatline implements its own “sub-theming” system, piggybacking on top of the capabilities provided by Omeka, that makes it possible to customize part or all of the appearance, layout, or behavior of each exhibit on an individual basis. This is an opt-in system that can be mixed with the regular, site-wide theming system – if you have 10 Neatline exhibits on your site, you could write exhibit-specific themes for three of them, and leave the other seven unchanged, allowing them to continue to inherit the generic Omeka theme. And, within the three exhibit-specific themes, you have full control over which parts of the theme you override – for one, you could leave the layout unchanged, but modify the CSS; for another, you could leave the CSS the same but change the layout and add some custom Javascript interactions. Exhibit-specific themes are also highly portable – once you’ve built one to your liking, it can be adapted for new exhibits just by copying and renaming the directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve held off on documenting this publicly because I wanted to be sure that the file structure and Javacsript APIs used in the themes worked well at scale – but at this point it’s all pretty battle tested, and I’m curious to see what other folks can come up with!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-started-creating-the-theme-directory&quot;&gt;Getting started: Creating the theme directory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neatline themes are created as directories that sit inside of the Omeka theme. For any given exhibit, Neatline will look for a theme directory that has the same name as the “URL slug” of the exhibit, the unique, plain-text identifier used to form the end of the exhibit’s public-facing URL. So, imagine you’ve got an exhibit called “Test Exhibit,” with a URL slug of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;test-exhibit&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. To create a theme for the exhibit, create a directory called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;test-exhibit&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; at this location relative to the root of your Omeka theme:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;[omeka-theme]/neatline/exhibits/themes/test-exhibit&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, here’s the layout of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/davidmcclure/neatlight&quot;&gt;my fork of the Neatlight theme&lt;/a&gt;, with the theme directories for a handful of exhibits at &lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/&quot;&gt;neatline.dclure.org&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/nltheme-tree.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/nltheme-tree.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nltheme-tree&quot; width=&quot;313&quot; height=&quot;372&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-10040&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anatomy-of-a-neatline-theme&quot;&gt;Anatomy of a Neatline theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neatline themes consist of just four files: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;script.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;show.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;item.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;stylecss&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to add custom CSS to the exhibit. Neatline loads this as the last stylesheet on the page, after the Omeka CSS and after the CSS provided by the Neatline core (which, if you want, can be omitted from the page by providing a custom &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;show.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; template – see below). &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; can be anything from a handful of simple rules to change fonts or colors up to a complete redesign of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;scriptjs&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;script.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;script.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to add custom Javascript interactions to the page. Again, these can be as simple or complex as needed. The Neatline front-end application is a big chunk of code, and it’s a bit beyond the scope of this article to really dive into the API in detail. The gist of it, though, is that Neatline is structured as a bunch of little mini-applications, called “modules,” that communicate with one another using a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Publish%E2%80%93subscribe_pattern&quot;&gt;pub-sub&lt;/a&gt; messaging system, powered by the superb &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/marionettejs/backbone.wreqr#event-aggregator&quot;&gt;EventAggregator component in the Marionette framework&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cool thing about this architecture is that snippets of code in the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;script.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; file can hook directly into this messaging system and interact with Neatline just as if they were included in the core codebase – Neatline literally won’t know the difference. There’s really no limit to what you could do here – the entire Neatline editing environment, for instance, is implemented as a single module (containing lots and lots of nested sub-modules), and could theoretically be grafted onto Neatline completely inside of an exhibit theme. This makes it possible to wrap up a Neatline exhibit in pretty much any kind of interface without having to modify the internals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, in most cases you’ll probably just need a few little snippets to add in some visual bells and whistles, or to manage complex layout tasks that are tough to accomplish in CSS. For example, here are a few snippets I used in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/logs/project-gemini-over-baja-california/&quot;&gt;Project Gemini over Baja California&lt;/a&gt; project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Position the text container on the left side of the screen and fill the height of the window:
&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Add an &lt;a href=&quot;http://ricostacruz.com/nprogress/&quot;&gt;NProgress&lt;/a&gt;-powered loading bar to the page:
&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Implement custom zooming buttons:
&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;
                &lt;p&gt;Add a “Loading Tiles…” spinner that displays when WMS imagery is being loaded from Geoserver:
&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;
For an example of a fully-fledged module, which follows the file layout conventions of the Neatline core, take a look at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/davidmcclure/neatlight/tree/master/neatline/exhibits/themes/gemini-over-baja-california/assets/javascripts/lines&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Lines&lt;/code&gt; module in the Gemini theme&lt;/a&gt;, which intercepts events broadcast by NeatlineText and draws the little yellow lines between the text and the map.&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;h1 id=&quot;showphp&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;show.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;By default, all Neatline exhibits are displayed using the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;show.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; that ships with the plugin. If you create a file called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;show.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in the exhibit theme, though, Neatline will use that file in place of the default. This makes it possible to completely customize the structure of the markup in any way you want. For example, if you look closely at some of the Jacascript examples above, you’ll notice that in a couple of places the code is selecting elements (things like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$('#wms-loader')&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$('div.narrative')&lt;/code&gt;) that aren’t actually templated anywhere in the default &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;show.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;This works, though, because I’m providing a custom &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;show.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; template that provides those elements (e.g., see the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#wms-loader&lt;/code&gt; element down near the bottom):&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;h1 id=&quot;itemphp&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;item.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;Last but not least, Neatline makes it possible to override the template that’s used to generate the metadata output for items displayed inside Neatline exhibits. By default, Neatline uses a simple template that pretty much just follows the layout of the regular item “show” pages in Omeka:&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;But, imagine you had an exhibit that was filled with items that represent photographs, and, for the sake of cleanliness and visual economy, you &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; want to display the item title and the image thumbnail. Just drop in a new &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;item.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; template that does exactly what you need:&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;And Neatline will automatically use that template instead of the default. What if you need different templates for different items, though? For example, imagine that you actually have two types of items in the exhibit – the images, which just need the title and thumbnail, but also a set of letters, which are structured as “Text” type items with the transcriptions of the documents entered into the “Text” field. So, how to display both types of items in the exhibit, without resorting to a weird, Frankenstein template that accommodates both?&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;First, add tags to the records in Neatline:&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/nltheme-tag.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/nltheme-tag-300x214.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nltheme-tag&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;214&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-medium wp-image-10043&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;Then, just create two template in the exhibit theme – one called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;item-image.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (the same as above), the other called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;item-letter.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In the letter template, just display the title and text:&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;Neatline will automatically use the tag-specific templates for any records tagged with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;image&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;letter&lt;/code&gt;, and fall back to the unadorned &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;item.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; template for records that aren’t tagged.&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;h2 id=&quot;starter-theme&quot;&gt;Starter theme&lt;/h2&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;So far, we’ve just been entering all of our custom CSS and Javascript directly into the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;script.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and files. This works fine for simple themes, but it can start to get a little clunky as the theme grows more complex – nobody likes to see a big heap of Javascript snippets, all doing different things, crammed into the same file. So, how to decompose &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;script.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; into separate files? One good solution is to use a task runner like &lt;a href=&quot;http://gruntjs.com/&quot;&gt;Grunt&lt;/a&gt; to concatenate multiple source files into the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;script.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; files, which, instead of being edited directly, become compiled payload files that are updated automatically by the task runner.&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/file-concatenation.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/file-concatenation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;file-concatenation&quot; width=&quot;233&quot; height=&quot;460&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-full wp-image-10050&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;To make it easy to get started, I’ve created a little starter theme, based on the theme used for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/logs/project-gemini-over-baja-california/&quot;&gt;Project Gemini over Baja California&lt;/a&gt; project, with all of the configuration and file structure in place to build out themes for exhibits that use the NeatlineText extension. This includes all of the layout, styling, and UX interactions from the Gemini project, like the little yellow lines that wire up the text with the map.&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/neatline-theme-template&quot;&gt;https://github.com/scholarslab/neatline-theme-template&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

                &lt;p&gt;Just fork the repo, clone it into your Omeka theme, and theme into the sunset!&lt;/p&gt;
              &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>dm4fn</name></author><summary type="html">Neatline makes it possible to create separate themes for individual exhibits, which is useful if you want to host a collection of self-contained Neatline projects on a single site. To get started, fork the exhibit starter theme, which abstracts out the style, layout, and UX of the Project Gemini over Baja California exhibit. One&amp;hellip;. More.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NeatlineText: Connect Neatline exhibits to documents</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/03/31/neatlinetext-connect-neatline-exhibits-to-documents/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NeatlineText: Connect Neatline exhibits to documents" /><published>2014-03-31T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-03-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2014/03/31/neatlinetext-connect-neatline-exhibits-to-documents</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2014/03/31/neatlinetext-connect-neatline-exhibits-to-documents/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Z3988&quot; title=&quot;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Focoins.info%3Agenerator&amp;amp;rft.type=&amp;amp;rft.format=text&amp;amp;rft.title=NeatlineText%3A+Connect+Neatline+exhibits+to+documents&amp;amp;rft.source=Scholars%26%23039%3B+Lab&amp;amp;rft.date=2014-03-31&amp;amp;rft.identifier=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.scholarslab.org%2Fannouncements%2Fneatline-text%2F&amp;amp;rft.language=English&amp;amp;rft.subject=Announcements&amp;amp;rft.aulast=McClure&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=David&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;download-the-plugin&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/add-ons/plugins/neatlinetext&quot;&gt;Download the plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/add-ons/plugins/neatlinetext&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/nltext-detail-1024x442.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nltext-detail&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;442&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-9950&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we’re pleased to announce the first public release of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/add-ons/plugins/neatlinetext&quot;&gt;NeatlineText&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which makes it possible to create interactive, Neatline-enhanced editions of text documents – literary and historical texts, articles, book chapters, dissertations, blog posts, etc. – by connecting individual paragraphs, sentences, and words with objects in Neatline exhibits. Once the associations are established, the plugin wires up two-way linkages in the user interface between the highlighted sections in the text and the imagery in the exhibit. Click on the text, and the exhibit focuses around the corresponding location or annotation. Or, click on the map, and the text scrolls to show the corresponding sections in the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been using some version of this code in internal projects here at the lab for almost two years, and it’s long overdue for a public release. The rationale for NeatlineText is pretty simple – again and again, we’ve found that Neatline projects often go hand-in-hand with some kind of regular text narrative that sets the stage, describes the goals of project, or lays out an expository thesis that would be hard to weave into the more visual, free-form world of the Neatline exhibit proper. This is awesome combination – tools like Neatline are really good at displaying spatial, visual, dimensional, diagrammatic information, but nothing beats plain old text when you need to develop a nuanced, closely-argued narrative or interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difficulty, though, is that it’s hard to combine the two in a way that doesn’t favor one over the other. We’ve taken quite a few whacks at this problem over the course of the last few years. One option is to present the text narrative as a kind of “front page” of the project that links out to the interactive environment. But this tends to make the Neatline exhibit feel like an add-on, something grafted onto the project as an after-thought. And this can easily become a self-fulfilling prophecy – when you have the click back and forth between different web pages to read the text and explore the exhibit, you tend to write the text as a more or less standalone piece of writing, instead of weaving the narrative in with the conceptual landscape of the exhibit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is to chop the prose narrative up into little chunks and build it directly into the exhibit – like the numbered waypoints we used in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hotchkiss.neatline.org/neatline-exhibits/show/chancellorsville-may-2-1863-132/fullscreen&quot;&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://hotchkiss.neatline.org/neatline-exhibits/show/battle-of-chancellorsville/fullscreen&quot;&gt;Hotchkiss&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://hotchkiss.neatline.org/neatline-exhibits/show/my-dear-little-nelly/fullscreen&quot;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; back in 2012, each waypoint containing a small portion of a longer interpretive essay. But this tends to err in the other direction, dissolving the text into the visual organization of the exhibit instead of presenting it as a first-class piece of content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NeatlineText tries to solves the problem by just plunking the two next to each other and making it easy for the reader (and the writer!) to move back and forth between the two. For example, NeatlineText powers the interactions between the text and imagery in &lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/gemini-over-baja-california&quot;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/saturn-v-stage-2&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; exhibits of NASA photograph from the 1960s:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/logs/project-gemini-over-baja-california/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/nltext-gemini-1024x619.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nltext-gemini&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;619&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-9941&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/saturn-v-stage-2&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/nltext-saturn-v-1024x615.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nltext-saturn-v&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;615&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-9942&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Yes, I know – I’m a space nerd.) NeatlineText is also great for creating interactive editions of primary texts. An earlier version of this code powers the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ships.lib.virginia.edu/neatline-editions/271&quot;&gt;Mapping the Catalog of Ships&lt;/a&gt; project by Jenny Strauss Clay, Courtney Evans, and Ben Jasnow (winner of the Fortier Prize prize at DH2013!), which connects the contingents in the Greek army mentioned in Book 2 of the Iliad with locations on the map:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ships.lib.virginia.edu/neatline-editions/271&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/nltext-ships-1024x614.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nltext-ships&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;614&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-9944&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And NeatlineText was also used in this interactive edition of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/gettysburg-address&quot;&gt;first draft of the Gettysburg Address&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/logs/nicolay-copy-gettysburg-address/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/nltext-gettysburg-1024x611.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nltext-gettysburg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;611&quot; class=&quot;aligncenter size-large wp-image-9943&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, grab the code from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/add-ons/plugins/neatlinetext&quot;&gt;Omeka add-ons repository&lt;/a&gt; and check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/nl-widget-Text#neatlinetext&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; for step-by-step instructions about how to get up and running. And, as always, be sure to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/nl-widget-Text/issues&quot;&gt;file a ticket&lt;/a&gt; if you run into problems!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>dm4fn</name></author><summary type="html">Download the plugin Today we&amp;rsquo;re pleased to announce the first public release of NeatlineText, which makes it possible to create interactive, Neatline-enhanced editions of text documents &amp;ndash; literary and historical texts, articles, book chapters, dissertations, blog posts, etc. &amp;ndash; by connecting individual paragraphs, sentences, and words with objects in Neatline exhibits. Once the associations are&amp;hellip;. More.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project Gemini over Baja California</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/03/17/project-gemini-over-baja-california/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Gemini over Baja California" /><published>2014-03-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-03-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2014/03/17/project-gemini-over-baja-california</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2014/03/17/project-gemini-over-baja-california/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Z3988&quot; title=&quot;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Focoins.info%3Agenerator&amp;amp;rft.type=&amp;amp;rft.format=text&amp;amp;rft.title=Project+Gemini+over+Baja+California&amp;amp;rft.source=Scholars%26%23039%3B+Lab&amp;amp;rft.date=2014-03-17&amp;amp;rft.identifier=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.scholarslab.org%2Fgeospatial-and-temporal%2Fproject-gemini-over-baja-california%2F&amp;amp;rft.language=English&amp;amp;rft.subject=Geospatial+and+Temporal&amp;amp;rft.aulast=McClure&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=David&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/logs/project-gemini-over-baja-california/&quot;&gt;dclure.org&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;launch-the-exhibit&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/gemini-over-baja-california&quot;&gt;Launch the Exhibit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/gemini-over-baja-california&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/gemini-screenshot-1024x615.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;gemini-screenshot&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;384&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3754&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple weeks ago, somewhere in the middle of a long session of free-association link hopping on Wikipedia, I stumbled into a cluster of articles about &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_Gemini&quot;&gt;Project Gemini&lt;/a&gt;, NASA’s second manned spaceflight program. Gemini, I quickly discovered, produced some spectacular photographs – many of them pointed downward towards the surface of the earth, capturing a dizzying opposition between the intelligible scale of the foreground (the 20-foot capsule, 100-foot tethering cords, 6-foot human bodies floating in space) and the completely unintelligible scale of the massive geographic entities below (peninsulas, continents, oceans).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started to click through the pictures, I found myself reflexively alt-tabbing back and forth between Chrome and Google Earth to compare them with the modern satellite imagery of the same geographic locations. Which made me think – why not try to actually combine the two into a single environment? Over the course of the next few days, I sketched out a little Neatline exhibit that plasters two photographs of Baja California Sur – taken about a year apart on Gemini 5 (August 1965) and Gemini 11 (September 1966) – around the Mapbox satellite imagery of the peninsula. Instead of lining up the coastlines to make the images overlay accurately on top of the satellite tiles, I just plunked them down on the map off to the side at a scale and orientation that makes it easy to compare the two. (We’ve &lt;a href=&quot;http://hotchkiss.neatline.org/neatline-exhibits/show/my-dear-little-nelly/fullscreen&quot;&gt;played around with this before&lt;/a&gt;, and I like to think of it as faux – or just especially humanistic! – georectification.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/faux-georectification.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/faux-georectification-1024x616.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;faux-georectification&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;385&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3774&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, using the drawing tools in Neatline, I blocked in some simple annotations that visually wire up the two sets of imagery – outlines around the four islands along the eastern coast of the peninsula, and arrows between the different instantiations of La Paz and San José del Cabo. I also wanted to find a way to visually formalize the difference in perspective between the Gemini photographs (oblique, wide-angle, deliberate) and the Mapbox tiles (flat-on, uniform). Using Illustrator, I created a long, ruler-like vector shape to label the ~200-mile distance between La Paz and the approximate positon of the Gemini 5 capsule when the picture was taken, and then used the “Perspective Grid” tool to render the shape in three dimensions and place it on top of the Gemini photograph, as if the same shape were physically positioned in front of the lens. In Illustrator:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/200-miles-illustrator.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/200-miles-illustrator-1024x564.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;200-miles-illustrator&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;352&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3767&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And placed in the Neatline exhibit, first to match the shallow angle of the Gemini shot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/200-miles.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/200-miles-1024x619.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;200-miles&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;386&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3764&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then to match the perpendicular angle of the Mapbox tiles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/200-miles-mapbox.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/200-miles-mapbox-1024x602.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;200-miles-mapbox&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;376&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3788&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also fascinated by the surreal opposition in scale between the Agena Target Vehicle (an unmanned spacecraft used for docking practice in orbit) and Isla San José, which sits serenely in the dark blue of the Gulf of California hundreds of miles below, but occupies almost exactly the same amount of space in the photograph as the 7-foot boom antenna on the Agena. In the space between the two, I dragged out two little shapes that map the sizes of things onto recognizable objects – a 6-foot person in the foreground, Manhattan in the background:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/manhattan-person.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/manhattan-person-1024x617.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;manhattan-person&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;385&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-large wp-image-3762&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Perspective and Perspectivelessness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These images fascinate me because they roll together two types of imagery – both ubiquitous on the web – that are almost exact opposites of one another. On the one hand, you have regular pictures, taken by regular (non-astronaut) people. These photographs freeze into place one particular &lt;em&gt;perspective&lt;/em&gt; on things. In a literal sense, the world recedes from the lens in three dimensions – walls, buildings, bridges, mountains, valleys, clouds. Close things are big, distant things are small. Some are in focus, others aren’t. And unlike other forms of art like painting, poetry, sculpture, or music, which can claim (overconfidently, maybe) to graft completely new material onto the world, photographs innovate at the level of &lt;em&gt;stance&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;viewpoint&lt;/em&gt;, the newness of the perspective on things that already exist. It’s less about what they add, more about what they subtract in order to whittle the world down to one particular frame. Why that angle? Why that moment? Why &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;, and not anything else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand you have spatial photography – the satellite imagery used in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps&quot;&gt;Google Maps&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mapbox.com/&quot;&gt;Mapbox&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bing.com/maps/&quot;&gt;Bing Maps&lt;/a&gt;, etc. – which is almost completely &lt;em&gt;perspectiveless&lt;/em&gt;, in just about every sense of the word. The world becomes a flat, depthless plane, photographed from a distance at a perpendicular angle. Instead of trying to find interesting new ways to crop down the world, spatial tiles try to be comprehensive and standardized. Instead of showing one thing, in one way, at one moment in time, they try to show everything, in the exact same way, at the exact same moment – now. The companies that source and assemble the satellite imagery race to keep it as current as possible, right at the threshold of the present. Last year, Google announced that its satellite imagery had been &lt;a href=&quot;http://google-latlong.blogspot.com/2013/06/only-clear-skies-on-google-maps-and.html&quot;&gt;purged of all clouds&lt;/a&gt;. No doubt this makes it more functional, but it also does away with those wispy, bright-white threads of cloud that used to hang over the rainforests in Peru and Brazil, which were lovely. What’s gained, of course, is the intoxicating grandeur of it all, the ability to hold in a single view a photograph of the entire world – which, if nothing else, is some sort of crazy affirmation of human willpower. I always imagine Whitman, scratching out “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bartelby.com/142/74.html&quot;&gt;Salut au Monde&lt;/a&gt;“, panning around Google Maps for inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photographs taken by astronauts, though, collapse the distinction in interesting ways. They’re literally “satellite” photography, but they’re also drenched in subjectivity and historical stance. The oceans and continents spread out hundreds of miles below, just like on Google Maps or Mapbox – but the pictures were snapped with regular cameras by the hands of actual people, stuffed into little canisters falling around the world at thousands of miles an hour, which were only up there in the first place due to a crazy mix of socio-political ambitions and anxieties that were deeply characteristic of that particular moment in history. The Gemini imagery is haloed with little bits of space-race technology that instantly historicizes the frame – the nose cone of the capsule blocks out a huge swath of desert and ocean, the Agena vehicle hangs just a couple of hundred feet from the camera, tethered by a slight, ribbon-like cord that twists for hundreds of miles across the Gulf of California.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>dm4fn</name></author><summary type="html">[Cross-posted from dclure.org] Launch the Exhibit A couple weeks ago, somewhere in the middle of a long session of free-association link hopping on Wikipedia, I stumbled into a cluster of articles about Project Gemini, NASA&amp;rsquo;s second manned spaceflight program. Gemini, I quickly discovered, produced some spectacular photographs &amp;ndash; many of them pointed downward towards the&amp;hellip;. More.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The “Nicolay copy” of the Gettysburg Address</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/02/04/the-nicolay-copy-of-the-gettysburg-address/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The “Nicolay copy” of the Gettysburg Address" /><published>2014-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2014/02/04/the-nicolay-copy-of-the-gettysburg-address</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2014/02/04/the-nicolay-copy-of-the-gettysburg-address/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Z3988&quot; title=&quot;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Focoins.info%3Agenerator&amp;amp;rft.type=&amp;amp;rft.format=text&amp;amp;rft.title=The+%22Nicolay+copy%22+of+the+Gettysburg+Address&amp;amp;rft.source=Scholars%26%23039%3B+Lab&amp;amp;rft.date=2014-02-04&amp;amp;rft.identifier=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.scholarslab.org%2Fexperimental-humanities%2Fneatline-gettysburg-address%2F&amp;amp;rft.language=English&amp;amp;rft.subject=Experimental+Humanities&amp;amp;rft.aulast=McClure&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=David&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from [dclure.org][1]]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;launch-the-exhibit2&quot;&gt;[Launch the Exhibit][2]&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/nicolay-fullscreen1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;nicolay-fullscreen&quot; width=&quot;2880&quot; height=&quot;1727&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3661&quot; /&gt;][2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a project that I’ve been hacking away at for some time, but only found the time (and motivation) to get it polished up and out the door over the weekend – a digital edition of the [“Nicolay copy” of the Gettysburg Address][3], with each of the ~250 words in the manuscript individually traced out in Neatline and wired up with a plain-text transcription of the text on the right side of the screen. I’ve tinkered around with [similar interfaces][4] in the past, but this time I wanted to play around with different approaches to formalizing the connection between the digitally-typeset words in the text and the handwritten words in the manuscript. Your eyes tend to dart back and forth between the image and the text, and it’s easy to lose your place – how to reduce that cognitive friction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To chip away at this, I wrote a little sub-plugin for Neatline called [WordLines][5], which automatically overlays a little visual guideline (under the hood, a [d3][6]-wrapped SVG `&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;line&gt;` element) on top of the page that connects each pair of words in the two viewports when the cursor hovers on either of the instantiations. So, when the mouse passes over words in the transcription, lines are automatically drawn to the corresponding locations on the image; and vice versa. From a technical standpoint, this turns out to be quite easy &amp;#8211; just get the pixel offsets for the `&lt;span&gt;` element in the transcription and the vector annotation on the map (for the latter, OpenLayers does the heavy lifting with helpers like `getViewPortPxFromLonLat`, which maps spatial coordinates to document-space pixel pairs), and then draw a line connecting the two points. The one hitch, though, is that this involves placing a large SVG element directly on top of the page content, which, by default, will cover all of the underlying elements (shapes on the map, words in the text) and block them from receiving the cursor events that drive the rest of the UI &amp;#8211; including, very problematically, the `mouseleave` event that garbage-collects old lines and prevents them from getting stuck on the screen.

[&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/wordline.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;wordline&quot; width=&quot;1470&quot; height=&quot;678&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3666&quot; /&gt;][7]

The work-around is to put `pointer-events: none;` on the SVG element, which causes the browser to treat it as a purely visual veneer over the page &amp;#8211; cursor events drop through to the underlying content elements, and everything else behaves normally. This is [just barely and only very recently cross-browser][8], but I&amp;#8217;m not sure if there&amp;#8217;s actually any other way to accomplish this, given the full set of constraints.

**Modeling intuitions about scale**

Originally, I had planned to just leave it at that, but, as is almost always the case with these projects, I ended up learning lots of interesting things along the way, and I ended up going back and adding in another set of annotations that make note of some of the more historically noteworthy aspects of the manuscript. Namely, I was interested in the different types of paper used for the two different pages (Lincoln probably wrote the first page in Washington before departing, the second page after arriving in Gettysburg) and the matching fold creases on the pages, which some historians have pointed to as evidence that the Nicolay copy was perhaps the actual &amp;#8220;reading copy&amp;#8221; that Lincoln used when delivering the speech, since eyewitness accounts describe Lincoln pulling a folded piece of paper out of his coat pocket.

The other candidate is the [Hay draft][9], which includes lots of changes and corrections in Lincoln&amp;#8217;s hand, giving it the appearance of working draft that was prepared just before the event. One problem with the Hays draft, though, is its size &amp;#8211; it&amp;#8217;s written on larger paper and has just a single fold down the center, which would seem to make it an unlikely thing to tuck into coat pocket. When I read about this, I realized that I had paid almost no attention to the physical size of the manuscript. On the screen, it&amp;#8217;s either extremely small or almost infinitely large &amp;#8211; a tiny speck when you zoom far back, and an endless plane of beige-and-black when you zoom in. But, in this case, size turns out to be of great historical significance &amp;#8211; the Nicolay copy is smaller than the Hays copy, especially when folded along the set of matching creases clearly visible on the pages.

So, how big is it? This involved a bit of guesswork. The resource page for the manuscript on the Library of Congress website doesn&amp;#8217;t include dimensions, and direct Google searches didn&amp;#8217;t turn up an easy answer, so I started poking around the internet to see if I could find other Lincoln manuscripts written on the &amp;#8220;Executive Stationery&amp;#8221; used for the first page. I rooted up a couple of documents for sale by rare book sellers, and in [both][10] [cases][11] the dimensions are listed at about 5 inches in width and 7-8 inches in height, meaning that the Nicolay copy &amp;#8211; assuming the stationery was more or less standardized &amp;#8211; would have folded down to a roughly 5 x 2.5-inch rectangle, which seems reasonably pocket-sized. (Again, this is amateur historical conjecture &amp;#8211; if I&amp;#8217;m wrong, please let me know!)

I sketched out little ruler annotations labeling the width of the page and the height of the fold segment, but, zooming around the exhibit, I realized that I still didn&amp;#8217;t any intuitive sense of the size of the thing. Raw numerical measurements, even when you&amp;#8217;re beat across the head with them, become surprisingly abstract in the a-physical, point-of-reference-less netherlands of deeply-zooming digital landscapes. I dug out a ruler and zoomed the exhibit back until the first page occupied five real-world inches, and then held my hand up to the screen, imagining the sheet of paper in my hand. And then I thought &amp;#8211; why not just bake some kind of visual reference directly into the exhibit? I hunted down a CC-licensed SVG illustration of a handprint, and, using the size of my own hand as a reference, used Neatline&amp;#8217;s import-SVG feature to position the outline in the whitespace to the right of the first page of the manuscript:

[&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/hand2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;hand2&quot; width=&quot;2106&quot; height=&quot;1524&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3664&quot; /&gt;][12]

 [1]: http://dclure.org/logs/nicolay-copy-gettysburg-address/
 [2]: http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/gettysburg-address
 [3]: http://prod.myloc.gov/Exhibitions/gettysburgaddress/exhibitionitems/ExhibitObjects/NicolayCopy.aspx
 [4]: http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/saturn-v-stage-2
 [5]: https://github.com/davidmcclure/nl-widget-WordLines
 [6]: http://d3js.org/
 [7]: http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/wordline.jpg
 [8]: http://caniuse.com/pointer-events
 [9]: http://prod.myloc.gov/Exhibitions/gettysburgaddress/exhibitionitems/ExhibitObjects/HayDraft.aspx
 [10]: http://www.baumanrarebooks.com/rare-books/lincoln-abraham/autograph-letter-signed/63126.aspx
 [11]: http://www.robertedwardauctions.com/auction/2006/1204.html
 [12]: http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/02/hand2.jpg
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/line&gt;</content><author><name>dm4fn</name></author><summary type="html">[Cross-posted from dclure.org] Launch the Exhibit This is a project that I&amp;rsquo;ve been hacking away at for some time, but only found the time (and motivation) to get it polished up and out the door over the weekend &amp;ndash; a digital edition of the &amp;ldquo;Nicolay copy&amp;rdquo; of the Gettysburg Address, with each of the ~250&amp;hellip;. More.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neatline release-apalooza: Neatline 2.2.0, Neatscape, Astrolabe</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2014/01/15/neatline-release-apalooza-neatline-2-2-0-neatscape-astrolabe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neatline release-apalooza: Neatline 2.2.0, Neatscape, Astrolabe" /><published>2014-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-01-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2014/01/15/neatline-release-apalooza-neatline-2-2-0-neatscape-astrolabe</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2014/01/15/neatline-release-apalooza-neatline-2-2-0-neatscape-astrolabe/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Z3988&quot; title=&quot;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Focoins.info%3Agenerator&amp;amp;rft.type=&amp;amp;rft.format=text&amp;amp;rft.title=Neatline+release-apalooza%3A+Neatline+2.2.0%2C+Neatscape%2C+Astrolabe&amp;amp;rft.source=Scholars%26%23039%3B+Lab&amp;amp;rft.date=2014-01-15&amp;amp;rft.identifier=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.scholarslab.org%2Fannouncements%2Fneatline-2-2-0%2F&amp;amp;rft.language=English&amp;amp;rft.subject=Announcements&amp;amp;rft.aulast=McClure&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=David&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
Today we’re excited to announce the release of Neatline 2.2.0! This is a big update that ships out a cluster of features and fixes that address a couple of rough spots identified by users over the course of the last couple months. 2.2.0 focuses on improvements in two areas – first, we’ve overhauled the workflows that connect Neatline records with Omeka items to make them more intuitive, flexible, and feature-rich, with the goal of making the overall integration between the two environments feel more seamless and low-friction. Second, we’ve added a system of interactive documentation to the editor that builds reference materials and tutorials directly into the interface, which should make it easier for new users to find their way around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re also pushing out maintenance releases of the two extensions, NeatlineSimile and NeatlineWaypoints, which add compatibility for Neatline 2.2 and deal with a couple of minor bugs. As always, grab the code from the Omeka addons repository:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/add-ons/plugins/neatline/&quot;&gt;Neatline 2.2.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/add-ons/plugins/neatlinesimile/&quot;&gt;NeatlineSimile 2.0.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/add-ons/plugins/neatlinewaypoints/&quot;&gt;NeatlineWaypoints 2.0.2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, we’re also making release candidates available for two new Omeka themes designed to showcase Neatline exhibits: &lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/add-ons/themes/astrolabe/&quot;&gt;Astrolabe&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/add-ons/themes/neatscape/&quot;&gt;Neatscape&lt;/a&gt;. Loyal readers may recall that a while back, we &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/announcements/neatline-omeka-theme-name-winners/&quot;&gt;ran a theme naming contest&lt;/a&gt;, and we’re finally making good on our word! These are just release candidates, but we wanted to get them out in the open for testing and feedback before cutting off stable releases. Give them a spin, and be sure to file a ticket on the respective issue trackers (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/astrolabe/issues&quot;&gt;Astrolabe&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/neatscape/issues&quot;&gt;Neatscape&lt;/a&gt;) if you find quirks or need new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some highlights in Neatline 2.2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adds a new interface for linking Neatline records to Omeka items&lt;/strong&gt; that makes it possible to browse the entire collection of items, run full-text searches, and instantaneously preview the Omeka content (metadata, images, etc.) as it will appear in the public Neatline exhibit. 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/item-binding.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/item-binding.gif&quot; alt=&quot;item-binding&quot; width=&quot;312&quot; height=&quot;771&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3379&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frees up the “Title” and “Body” fields for modification on Neatline records linked to Omeka items&lt;/strong&gt;. Previously, these fields were automatically populated with the item content imported from Omeka, making it impossible to add custom information not contained in the Omeka metadata. Now, Neatline leaves these fields open for editing and displays them above the content synced in from Omeka, making it possible (though not required) to add exhibit-specific headings and text descriptions for imported items.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Makes it possible to import raw data from the Dublin Core “Coverage” field&lt;/strong&gt;. When Omeka items are imported into Neatline exhibits, existing values in the Dublin Core “Coverage” field (either KML or WKT strings) are now automatically imported into Neatline and displayed on the map. Previously, this only worked if the coverage on the item was created with the Neatline Features plugin. With this functionality in place, it’s much easier to bulk-import existing spatial data sets – use the &lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/add-ons/plugins/csv-import/&quot;&gt;CSV Import&lt;/a&gt; plugin to populate a collection of items, and then push the new items to a Neatline exhibit.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adds interactive documentation to the editor&lt;/strong&gt; that builds reference materials for each individual control directly into the interface. Now, the heading for each input is followed by a little “&lt;strong&gt;?&lt;/strong&gt;” button that, when clicked, overlays a document with information about what the control does, how to use it, and how it interacts with other functionality. The goal is to make the editor effectively self-documenting, so that it’s unnecessary to find separate documentation and toggle back and forth between different tabs as you work. 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/interactive-docs.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/interactive-docs.gif&quot; alt=&quot;interactive-docs&quot; width=&quot;1261&quot; height=&quot;771&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3381&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last semester was a busy one for Neatline – we were supporting twelve classes here at UVa that are using Neatline for research assignments, and had the good fortune to collaborate with a number of folks at Harvard, Stanford, Northeastern, Duke, Indiana, and elsewhere who were using Neatline or gearing up for upcoming projects in the new year. We’ve also got a couple of exciting ideas brewing here in the lab for new, Neatline-powered projects – keep an eye on this space over the course of the next couple months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, don’t hesitate to file bug reports on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scholarslab/Neatline/issues&quot;&gt;issue tracker&lt;/a&gt;, post questions to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/forums/forum/plugins&quot;&gt;forums&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:neatline@collab.itc.virginia.edu&quot;&gt;contact us directly&lt;/a&gt;. Happy new year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>dm4fn</name></author><summary type="html">Today we&amp;rsquo;re excited to announce the release of Neatline 2.2.0! This is a big update that ships out a cluster of features and fixes that address a couple of rough spots identified by users over the course of the last couple months. 2.2.0 focuses on improvements in two areas &amp;ndash; first, we&amp;rsquo;ve overhauled the workflows&amp;hellip;. More.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neighborhoods of San Francisco</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2013/12/11/neighborhoods-of-san-francisco/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neighborhoods of San Francisco" /><published>2013-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2013-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2013/12/11/neighborhoods-of-san-francisco</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2013/12/11/neighborhoods-of-san-francisco/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Z3988&quot; title=&quot;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Focoins.info%3Agenerator&amp;amp;rft.type=&amp;amp;rft.format=text&amp;amp;rft.title=Neighborhoods+of+San+Francisco&amp;amp;rft.source=Scholars%26%23039%3B+Lab&amp;amp;rft.date=2013-12-11&amp;amp;rft.identifier=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.scholarslab.org%2Fgeospatial-and-temporal%2Fneatline-san-francisco%2F&amp;amp;rft.language=English&amp;amp;rft.subject=Geospatial+and+Temporal&amp;amp;rft.aulast=McClure&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=David&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/essays/neighborhoods-of-san-francisco/&quot;&gt;dclure.org&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;view-the-exhibit&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/neighborhoods-of-san-francisco&quot;&gt;View the Exhibit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/neighborhoods-of-san-francisco&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/neighborhoods-of-san-francisco.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;neighborhoods-of-san-francisco&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;980&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3355&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Built on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://maps.stamen.com/#toner/12/37.7706/-122.3782&quot;&gt;Stamen Toner layer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in October, about a month after moving from Scholars’ Lab HQ in Virginia out to Menlo Park (my partner started a PhD program at Stanford), I drove up the peninsula to San Francisco on a Saturday morning and set out on a long, rambling, 10-mile trek along the northwest shoulder of the city. It was a fantastic day – I walked west through Golden Gate Park, north along the Richmond beach, past the Cliff House, into the fog over Lincoln Park, through the mansions in Sea Cliff, past the abandoned artillery nests on the western coast of the Presidio, and finally out onto the Golden Gate bridge. From there, I headed south through the trails in the Presidio, into Richmond, and eventually back to where I started, near the top right corner of the park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the middle of the Golden Gate Bridge, you can look out to the east over a large swath of the city – the skyscrapers of the financial district, the new span of the Bay Bridge hanging over Treasure Island, Alcatraz, and the faded outline of the East Bay, the Berkeley campus a little smudge at the base of the ridge line. But, scanning my eyes over the rest of the city, I realized that I had very little sense of what I was actually looking at. I could attach labels onto all the touristy landmarks, but I didn’t have any kind of intuitive mental geography of the place – the names of all the little hills and neighborhoods, what connects to what, how to string the pieces of the city together into workable routes and itineraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, over the course of the next few weeks, I slowly cobbled together a &lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/neighborhoods-of-san-francisco&quot;&gt;Neatline exhibit&lt;/a&gt; that plots out each of the neighborhoods in the city – 87 of them, by my count, although it’s somewhat a matter of interpretation as to how they should be sliced and diced. Working mainly from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reocities.com/mwarren_us/sf-neighborhoods/SFNeighborhoods.gif&quot;&gt;this image&lt;/a&gt; as reference, I started by tracing rough outlines of the boundaries (using Neatline’s standard-issue “Draw Polygon” tool) on top of Stamen’s Toner layer. Then, once the borders were in place, I used Neatline’s SVG import tool to place vector-geometry text labels on top of each of the individual neighborhoods, inspired by other spatial-wordcloud experiments like &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfsgeography.wikispaces.com/file/view/SF_neighborhhods.jpg/184285923/SF_neighborhhods.jpg&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.californiatravel.eu/travel/NeighborhoodsofSanFrancisco.jpg&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adventures in geospatial typesetting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was great fun, and, interestingly, it ended up overlapping in unexpected ways with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/essays/experimental-typesetting-with-neatline-and-shakespeare/&quot;&gt;interactive&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/essays/more-fun-with-interactive-typesetting-a-coat-by-yeats/&quot;&gt;typesetting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/essays/song-of-wandering-aengus/&quot;&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; that I was playing with earlier in the semester. The process of positioning the labels becomes a kind of textual jigsaw puzzle, a game of trying to wrangle the raw, geometric instantiations of words into a coherent organizational scheme – except, this time, against the backdrop of actual geospatial coordinates and locations, not the abstract, featureless voids of the poetry experiments. Often, this is pretty straightforward – Noe Valley and the Inner Mission, for example, just get tagged as such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/noe-valley-inner-mission.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/noe-valley-inner-mission.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;noe-valley-inner-mission&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;788&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3312&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other places, though, the names of the neighborhoods overlap with one another in ways that make it possible to find interesting “economies” in how the words can be laid out on the map – when adjacent neighborhoods share the same words, it’s sometimes possible to essentially atomize the names into their component parts, and then rebuild them according to their own spatial logic, in a sense, by visually stringing together the pieces on the map. Take Richmond, for example, which is divided into three side-by-side segments: Outer Richmond, Central Richmond, and Inner Richmond. Instead of cluttering things up by repeating “Richmond” for each of the three sections, I just dragged out a single, all-encompassing “Richmond” across the entire width of the three sub-neighborhoods, and the blocked in the three modifiers as smaller words on top of the corresponding sections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/richmond.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/richmond.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;richmond&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;412&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3314&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This worked much the same way for the Sunset and Parkside neighborhoods, which share the same cleanly partitioned spatial organization:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/sunset.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/sunset.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;sunset&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;383&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3316&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the exception of the “middle” portion of Parkside, which is just the un-prefixed “Parkside,” meaning that the center piece doesn’t get a separate modifier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/parkside.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/parkside.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;parkside&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;590&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3318&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other cases, though, it gets much trickier, and much more interesting. Take the little cluster of neighborhoods at the southwest corner of the Presidio, the big park at the base of the Golden Gate Bridge. It’s a hodgepodge of repeated names, but in a much more scrambled and overlapping way – Presidio, Presidio Heights, Pacific Heights, Lower Pacific Heights. In this case, I had to take a bit more care to place the little black arrows in ways that didn’t connote incorrect linkages among the names. For example, the relationship between Presidio and Presidio Heights moves in just one direction – Presidio Heights (labelled with just “Heights” on the map) needs to “inherit” the “Presidio” modifier from the Presidio, but not the other way around, since the Presidio ceases to be the Presidio when “Heights” is tacked onto it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/presidio.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/presidio.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;presidio&quot; width=&quot;1000&quot; height=&quot;467&quot; class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-3319&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To encode these relationships, I settled on a rule of thumb that the arrows would always be &lt;em&gt;contained inside the neighborhoods that they modify&lt;/em&gt;. So, the arrow pointing from “Presidio” to “Heights” is fully contained inside of the geographic boundaries of Presidio Heights, in the sense that it pulls “Presidio” downward into the “Heights,” without also pushing “Heights” back in the other direction (which would effectively mislabel the Presidio). Likewise the link between “Pacific” and “Heights” is contained within the Pacific Heights outline, since otherwise Presidio Heights would be implicitly but incorrectly prefixed by “Pacific.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is all completely useless as actual cartographic practice, but great fun as a kind of abstract &lt;em&gt;étude&lt;/em&gt; of information design. It’s also incredibly useful as a mnemonic device – after untold hours in Palo Alto coffee shops sketching out all the outlines and positioning the labels, they’re all thoroughly burned into my mind. This is an interesting aspect of digital mapping projects that doesn’t get a lot of attention – we tend to focus on the final products, the public-facing visualizations and interactions (for good and obvious reasons), but much less on the &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; that goes into creating them, the personal acquisition of knowledge that takes place when you force yourself to spend dozens or hundreds of hours painstakingly positioning and repositioning things on maps. It gives you an incredible sense of cognitive intimacy with the space, the ability to load a little chunk of the world into working memory and reason about it in really complex and interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>dm4fn</name></author><summary type="html">[Cross-posted from dclure.org] View the Exhibit Built on the Stamen Toner layer. Back in October, about a month after moving from Scholars&amp;rsquo; Lab HQ in Virginia out to Menlo Park (my partner started a PhD program at Stanford), I drove up the peninsula to San Francisco on a Saturday morning and set out on a&amp;hellip;. More.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NITLE Presentation on Geotemporal Storytelling with Neatline</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2013/10/14/nitle-presentation-on-geotemporal-storytelling-with-neatline/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NITLE Presentation on Geotemporal Storytelling with Neatline" /><published>2013-10-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-10-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2013/10/14/nitle-presentation-on-geotemporal-storytelling-with-neatline</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2013/10/14/nitle-presentation-on-geotemporal-storytelling-with-neatline/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Z3988&quot; title=&quot;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Focoins.info%3Agenerator&amp;amp;rft.type=&amp;amp;rft.format=text&amp;amp;rft.title=NITLE+Presentation+on+Geotemporal+Storytelling+with+Neatline&amp;amp;rft.source=Scholars%26%23039%3B+Lab&amp;amp;rft.date=2013-10-14&amp;amp;rft.identifier=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.scholarslab.org%2Fdigital-humanities%2Fnitle-presentation-on-geotemporal-storytelling-with-neatline%2F&amp;amp;rft.language=English&amp;amp;rft.subject=Digital+Humanities&amp;amp;rft.subject=Geospatial+and+Temporal&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Boggs&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Jeremy&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
About this time last year, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scholarslab.org/people/david-mcclure/&quot;&gt;David McClure&lt;/a&gt; and I had a great conversation with the folks from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nitle.org/&quot;&gt;National Institute for Technology in Liberal Education (NITLE)&lt;/a&gt; about geotemporal storytelling with &lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.org/&quot;&gt;Neatline&lt;/a&gt;. We had lots of great questions and comments from the audience, too. Video for the talk is now available on NITLE’s YouTube channel:&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jeremy Boggs</name></author><summary type="html">About this time last year, David McClure and I had a great conversation with the folks from the National Institute for Technology in Liberal Education (NITLE) about geotemporal storytelling with Neatline. We had lots of great questions and comments from the audience, too. Video for the talk is now available on NITLE&amp;rsquo;s YouTube channel:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“The Song of Wandering Aengus,” Neatline, and negotiation with the machine</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2013/10/11/the-song-of-wandering-aengus-neatline-and-negotiation-with-the-machine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“The Song of Wandering Aengus,” Neatline, and negotiation with the machine" /><published>2013-10-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-10-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2013/10/11/the-song-of-wandering-aengus-neatline-and-negotiation-with-the-machine</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2013/10/11/the-song-of-wandering-aengus-neatline-and-negotiation-with-the-machine/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Z3988&quot; title=&quot;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Focoins.info%3Agenerator&amp;amp;rft.type=&amp;amp;rft.format=text&amp;amp;rft.title=%22The+Song+of+Wandering+Aengus%2C%22+Neatline%2C+and+negotiation+with+the+machine&amp;amp;rft.source=Scholars%26%23039%3B+Lab&amp;amp;rft.date=2013-10-11&amp;amp;rft.identifier=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.scholarslab.org%2Fexperimental-humanities%2Fsong-of-wandering-aengus%2F&amp;amp;rft.language=English&amp;amp;rft.subject=Experimental+Humanities&amp;amp;rft.aulast=McClure&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=David&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/song-of-wandering-aengus&quot;&gt;dclure.org&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;click-here-to-view-the-exhibit&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/song-of-wandering-aengus&quot;&gt;Click here to view the exhibit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last little experiment with Neatline-powered interactive typesettings – this time with the ending of Yeats’ endlessly recitable “The Song of Wandering Aengus,” which, like many great poems, seems to somehow signify the entire world and nothing really in particular. I chose to use just the last three lines so that it would be possible to play with a more dramatic type of geometric nesting that, with more content, would quickly run up against the technical limitation that I mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/essays/more-fun-with-interactive-typesetting-a-coat-by-yeats/&quot;&gt;Wednesday’s post about “A Coat”&lt;/a&gt; – the vector geometry used to form the letters starts to degrade as the Javascript environment runs out of decimal precision at around 40 levels of zoom, making it impossible to continue the downward beyond a certain point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With just three lines, though, I was able to place each consecutive line completely inside of one of the dots above an “i” in the previous line. So, the “silver apples of the moon” are inscribed into the dot over the “i” in the “till” of “till time and times are done,” and the “golden apples of the moon” are then contained by the dot on the “i” in “silver.” Since the nested lines are placed literally inside the shaded boundaries of letters (as opposed to the empty spaces delineated by the “holes” in letters, as was the case with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/essays/more-fun-with-interactive-typesetting-a-coat-by-yeats/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/essays/experimental-typesetting-with-neatline-and-shakespeare/&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; experiments), the color of the text has to alternate in order to be legible against the changing color of the backdrop. What I didn’t expect (although in retrospect I guess it’s obvious) is that this shift in the color palette completely modulates the visual temperature of the whole environment – the backdrop swerves from bright white to solid black back and then back to white over the course of the three lines, with the last transition mapping onto the night-to-day, moon-to-sun thematic movement in the final couplet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this effect was almost thwarted by another unexpected quirk in the underlying technologies, although I managed to maneuver around it with a little hack in the exhibit theme. The problem was this – it turns out that OpenLayers will actually stop rendering an SVG geometry ones the dimension of the viewport shrinks down below a certain ratio relative to the overall size of the shape. So, in this case, as the camera descends down into the black landscape of the dot over the first “i,” the black background supplied by the vector shape would suddenly drop away, as if the camera were falling through the surface, which of course had the effect of making the second-to-last line – typeset in white – suddenly invisible against the default-white background of the exhibit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this was a showstopper, but then I realized that I could programmatically “fake” the black background by directly flipping the CSS &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;background&lt;/code&gt; color on the exhibit container. So, I just fired up the Javascript console, inspected the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;zoom&lt;/code&gt; attribute on the OpenLayers instance to get the zoom thresholds where the color changes needed to happen, and then dropped a little chunk of custom code into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/davidmcclure/neatlight/tree/master/neatline/exhibits/themes/song-of-wandering-aengus&quot;&gt;exhibit theme&lt;/a&gt; that manifests the style change in response to the zoom events triggered by the map:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weird, but effective. Whenever I work on projects like these I’m fascinated by the wrinkles that arise in the interaction between what you want to do and what the technology allows you to do. It’s very different from analog scholarship or art practice, where you have a more complete mastery over the field of play – you have a much more direct and unmediated control over the sound of your words, the shape of a line in a physical sketch, the pressure of a brush stroke. With digital objects, though, you’re building on top of almost unimaginably huge stacks of technology – the millions of man-hours of work that it took to create the vast ecosystem of Javascript and PHP libraries that Neatline depends on, the whole set of lower-level technologies that shape the underlying browser rendering engines and Javascript runtimes, which in turn are implemented in still lower-level languages, which eventually brush up against the dizzying rabbit hole of physical hardware engineering, which to my mind is about as close to magic as anything that people have produced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That kind of deep, massively-distributed collaboration can definitely exist offscreen (eg., all of intellectual history, in a sense), but it’s more loosely coupled, and certainly less fragile – if I write an essay about Yeats, Yeats can’t &lt;em&gt;break&lt;/em&gt; in the way that a code dependency literally can (will). At first this really bothered me, but I’ve come to peace with it – digital work is by definition a relinquishing of control, a give-and-take with the machine, a negotiation with our current little slice of modernity about what’s possible.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>dm4fn</name></author><summary type="html">[Cross-posted from dclure.org] Click here to view the exhibit. One last little experiment with Neatline-powered interactive typesettings &amp;ndash; this time with the ending of Yeats&amp;rsquo; endlessly recitable &amp;ldquo;The Song of Wandering Aengus,&amp;rdquo; which, like many great poems, seems to somehow signify the entire world and nothing really in particular. I chose to use just the&amp;hellip;. More.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">More fun with interactive typesetting: “A Coat,” by Yeats</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2013/10/09/more-fun-with-interactive-typesetting-a-coat-by-yeats/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="More fun with interactive typesetting: “A Coat,” by Yeats" /><published>2013-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2013-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2013/10/09/more-fun-with-interactive-typesetting-a-coat-by-yeats</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2013/10/09/more-fun-with-interactive-typesetting-a-coat-by-yeats/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;Z3988&quot; title=&quot;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adc&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Focoins.info%3Agenerator&amp;amp;rft.type=&amp;amp;rft.format=text&amp;amp;rft.title=More+fun+with+interactive+typesetting%3A+%22A+Coat%2C%22+by+Yeats&amp;amp;rft.source=Scholars%26%23039%3B+Lab&amp;amp;rft.date=2013-10-09&amp;amp;rft.identifier=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.scholarslab.org%2Fexperimental-humanities%2Fmore-fun-with-interactive-typesetting-a-coat-by-yeats%2F&amp;amp;rft.language=English&amp;amp;rft.subject=Experimental+Humanities&amp;amp;rft.aulast=McClure&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=David&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;em&gt;[Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/essays/more-fun-with-interactive-typesetting-a-coat-by-yeats/&quot;&gt;dclure.org&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;click-here-to-view-the-exhibit&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.dclure.org/neatline/show/a-coat&quot;&gt;Click here to view the exhibit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After spending the weekend &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/essays/experimental-typesetting-with-neatline-and-shakespeare/&quot;&gt;tinkering around with an interactive typesetting of a couplet from Macbeth&lt;/a&gt; that tried to model reading as a process of zooming &lt;em&gt;downward&lt;/em&gt; towards the end of the phrase, I became curious about experimenting with the opposite analogy – reading as an &lt;em&gt;upward&lt;/em&gt; movement, an climb from the bottom (the beginning) to the top (the end), with each word circumscribing everything that comes before it. Really, this is just the flip side of the same coin. Meaning certainly flows “downhill” in a phrase – each word is informed by the previous word. But it also flows back “uphill” – each word casts new meaning onto what comes before it. What would it would feel like to visualize that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I decided to work with “A Coat,” Yeats’ wonderful little ode to simplicity (he renounces what he thinks to be the stylistic affectation of his work from the 1890’s, and announces an intention to write “naked[ly]“). Originally, I planned to exactly invert the layout of the Macbeth couplet – start with the “I” at the bottom of the stack, and work upwards towards the end with “naked,” which, in the final frame, would geometrically contain each of the preceding words. I started to do this, but quickly ran into an interesting computational obstacle, which actually cropped up in the Shakespeare example as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trip Kirkpatrick noticed the problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/clured&quot;&gt;@clured&lt;/a&gt; Are jaggies on deepest zoom artifacts results of zoomed pixels or aesthetic decisions? Both?
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;mdash; Trip Kirkpatrick (@triplingual) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/triplingual/statuses/387254660563992576&quot;&gt;October 7, 2013&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the last two words – “way” and “comes” – are pixelated and malformed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/way.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/way-300x151.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;way&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;151&quot; class=&quot;size-medium wp-image-3114&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/comes.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/comes-300x93.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;comes&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;93&quot; class=&quot;size-medium wp-image-3113&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t on purpose – I couldn’t figure out why it was happening when I was working on the exhibit, but decided against trying to fix it, half out of laziness and half because the visual effect had some satisfying affinities with the content of the line, especially when paired with the “descending” motif – a plunge down to hell, where order disintegrates, smooth lines are forbidden, etc. Anyway – after thinking it over, I’m pretty sure I know what’s going on, although I’m not certain. At the extremely deep zoom levels (far beyond anything you’d ever need for a regular map), I think that OpenLayers is actually losing the floating point precision that it needs to accurately plot the SVG paths for the letters – the computer is running out of decimal places, essentially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I squeaked by with the Macbeth couplet, but this turned out to be a showstopper for the Yeats, since I was effectively trying to plot geometry about four and a half times deeper – 45 words versus 11. At that depth, the text becomes completely illegible, so I had to find a way to squeeze more content into fewer zoom levels. In the end, I managed to fit it all in by positioning each line into a geometric “notch” formed by the ascenders of two letters on the following line, which more or less preserves the philosophical rationale of the exhibit (each bit of text “envelops” the previous, if somewhat less completely than before) while limiting the zooming to just ten magnification contexts, one for each line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/heel.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://dclure.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/heel-300x114.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;heel&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;114&quot; class=&quot;size-medium wp-image-3131&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To scan the poem, just zoom out by clicking on the “minus” button (or scrolling the mouse wheel or pinching the screen, if applicable), or click on the lines in the reference text at the top left to auto-focus on a particular part of the poem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>dm4fn</name></author><summary type="html">[Cross-posted from dclure.org] Click here to view the exhibit. After spending the weekend tinkering around with an interactive typesetting of a couplet from Macbeth that tried to model reading as a process of zooming downward towards the end of the phrase, I became curious about experimenting with the opposite analogy &amp;ndash; reading as an upward&amp;hellip;. More.</summary></entry></feed>